我相信你最近在各种内容下面
I'm sure you've seen comments like this all over the internet lately.
应该都见过这样一句类似的评论
那几个月之前
A few months ago,
其实大家把这个当成一种调侃了
people mostly said it as a joke,
是一种梗 对吧
like a meme, right?
你看到太离谱的东西
When you saw something ridiculous,
你会说
you'd say,
哎呀这是AI或者AI太好用了家人
"Come on, that's AI," or "AI is way too good now, folks."
但有意思就是只过了短短几个月
But what's interesting is that in just a few short months,
你会发现现在这句 这是AI吗
the question, "Is this AI?"
背后的情绪
has taken on a completely different feeling.
它变化了
因为AI它又变强了
Because AI has gotten even better.
所以现在互联网内容消费环境
So I think the way we consume content online now
我觉得开始进入一种
is starting to feel like
抓狐狸尾巴的状态
a constant game of spotting the fox's tail.
那我说的不只是国内
And I'm not just talking about China,
而是全球内容消费者
I mean content consumers worldwide.
我自己也是这个消费者
I'm one of them too.
你有没有过近似的体验
Have you ever had an experience like this?
就是你点开一个新的内容
You click on a new piece of content,
现在你可能根本没在关注内容本身
and instead of paying attention to the content itself,
而是在看背景里的文字有没有扭曲
you're looking for warped text in the background,
数人手上有几根手指
counting how many fingers someone in the video has,
尝试辨别
trying to figure out,
这到底是不是由一台电脑
is this actually a computer-made
做给我的所谓的真人的真实视频
so-called real video of a real person made for me?
可是另一方面
But on the other hand,
我自己也是做视频的人
I make videos too.
我挺希望观众
And I really hope viewers
不是这样来看我们的内容
aren't watching our content that way.
因为情绪就完全混乱了
Because it completely scrambles the emotional experience.
所以是一个超级矛盾的状态
So it's an incredibly contradictory situation.
但这就是我们这个视频想来和你聊的
And that's exactly what we want to talk about in this video.
在2026年中段这个时间
Here in the middle of 2026,
我觉得AI已经强到了一个地步
I think AI has become so powerful
它开始进入快速摧毁
that it's entering a phase of rapidly eroding trust
互联网信任的阶段
on the internet.
那首先讨厌或者质疑AI的情绪
First, the dislike of AI, or skepticism toward AI
其实很好理解
is pretty easy to understand.
因为AI内容很容易被关联到两个词上
Because AI-generated content is often associated with two things:
就是劣质和偷懒
low quality and laziness.
那我不是说现在没有好的AI内容
I'm not saying there's no good AI content out there.
你说做得好的
There are good ones,
像这种很有想法的AI短片
like these creative AI shorts,
还有这种水果短剧
or these fruit-themed mini dramas,
你不能说它不好 对吧
you can't really say they're bad, right?
确实很搞笑也很魔性
They're genuinely funny and weirdly addictive.
我也看
I watch them too.
但是这些AI内容之所以受欢迎
But the reason these AI videos are popular
是因为作者借助AI这个工具
is because their creators used AI as a tool
花费了大量的精力去打磨
and put a huge amount of effort into refining them,
是值得敬佩的
which deserves respect.
但是毕竟好的内容是少数
But good content is still the minority.
大部分目前我们看到的AI作品是这种
Most of the AI content we see right now looks more like this:
乱七八糟的文字
nonsensical text,
错误的视频信息
incorrect visual information.
比如你看这个
Take this for example.
这个俯卧撑 手都飞到另一边去了
For the push-up image, the hands are flying to the sky.
这是绝对侮辱我们的智商
That's an insult to our intelligence.
那当然该骂
Of course it's a shame.
对吧 这完全应该
Totally, right?
但这是之前的情况
But that was the situation before.
因为我们分得出来什么是AI
Because we could tell what was AI,
所以我们可以骂或者不看
so we could mock it or just ignore it.
但就是最近这五个月
But over the last five months or so,
AI它进化了
AI has evolved.
比如这两张图片放在一起
Now, if I put these two images side by side,
你能分清楚哪个是AI的聊天记录吗
can you tell which WeChat screenshot was generated by AI?
那么好 我们公布答案
Alright, here's the answer.
左边这个是伪造的
The left one is fake.
你可能以为AI是伪造了聊天软件的界面这个图片
You might think AI just faked the WeChat interface in that image.
但事实上这整个图
But in reality, the entire picture,
就这整个图包括指纹 这个手机
the fingerprint smudges on the screen, the phone itself,
没有一个是真的
none of it is real.
这就变得非常奇怪了
And that's the weird part.
哪怕你再有经验
No matter how experienced you are,
你很难一眼分辨出来
it's hard to tell at a glance
这样的视频 这样的图片
whether a video or an image like this,
是不是AI
was made by AI.
我都不确定
If I'm not sure myself,
那我该怎么表达我的情绪呢
how am I supposed to react?
那这个时候我们唯一能做的就是
At that point, the only thing we can do
不管看到什么
is ask ourselves, no matter what we see:
好像都得先问一句
这是AI吗
"Is this AI?"
我们都开始不由自主地
We've all started, almost unconsciously,
不再信任互联网上的内容
to stop trusting what we see online.
是那种非常底层的不信任
And I mean a very fundamental kind of distrust,
就是一个像素都不能信的那种
the kind where you don't trust a single pixel.
但恰恰好
But the thing is,
信任又是互联网上最大的杠杆
trust has always been the internet's biggest lever.
一边是作者
Creators on one side,
另一边是观众和情绪
the other side are audiences and their emotions.
大家能够平衡好了
When that balance works,
大家都会很开心
everyone can be happy.
你只有相信这是一个人认真拍的东西
You only feel moved if you believe a real person made it sincerely.
你才会感动
你相信这是一个人花了几年
You only admire someone's work
研究出来的东西
when you believe they spent years
你才会欣赏他
figuring it out.
但如果现在我们脑子的第一情绪
But if the first thing that comes to mind now
变成了疑问句
is a question mark,
那有相当长的一段时间
then for a significant amount of time,
我们是脱离作者的情绪的
we're disconnected from the creator's emotions.
我们在甄别 在怀疑
We're analyzing, we're doubting.
这是一种被动的解构
It's a kind of passive deconstruction.
以前互联网信任建立真的很快的
Trust used to form really quickly on the internet.
但现在这个支点在不断地后移
But now it's getting harder and harder to earn.
不管是在你的内容上
Whether you're watching content
还是评论区和人交流
or talking to people in the comments,
你都在怀疑他是不是人
you're wondering if there's even a real person.
就很多内容已经撬不动情绪了
Many content just can't trigger an emotional response anymore.
而且更糟糕的是这种变化
And what's worse,
不只是针对视频
this shift isn't limited to video,
你要发现图片 文字
images, text,
各种形态的都在经历一样的事情
every format is going through the same thing.
做东西最爽的其实是
The best parts of creating something
找到认可和知音
is finding people who truly get it.
看到大家的互动和评论
Seeing people's reactions and comments,
这种人感是很重要的
that human connection matters.
可是如果评论里面充满了类似
But when the comments are filled with things like,
这是AI做的
"This was made by AI,"
为什么不标AI这样的评论
or "Why didn't you label this as AI?"
但如果这恰好是一个真的用心
and the creator actually spent real effort,
用手工
working by hand,
花了AI上千倍时间
spending a thousand times longer than AI would,
做了内容的创作者
to make that piece of content,
本来期待能找到有共鸣的观众
hoping it would resonate with people,
看到这样的疑问句
seeing those kinds of comments,
你说不难受是假的
of course it hurts.
但这根本就不是观众的问题
But this really isn't the audience's fault.
只是因为AI太像人了
It's that AI has become too human-like.
创作的正向循环正在被快速削弱
The positive feedback loop of creation is being weakened quickly.
AI和真人的产效差距又太大
And the productivity gap between AI and humans is becoming enormous.
这对手工的作者
For creators who do things by hand,
就是有点绝望的事情
that can feel pretty hopeless.
尤其是现在的第二代模型
Especially with the second generation of models today.
我不知道你没有了解过
I don't know if you've been following this stuff,
我是这么叫它的
that's what I call them.
它们开始渗透进入所有的软件里面了
They're starting to make their way into every piece of software.
传统的这些大的软件
A lot of the traditional major apps
反而变成了这些AI模型的插件
have almost become plugins for AI models instead.
这使得AI把整个学习曲线给拆掉了
And that has basically flattened the entire learning curve.
你不需要懂软件
No need to learn software,
你只要会说话
you can just use voice commands.
比如现在我对AI说
Like, I can tell an AI,
给我做这样一个东西
make something like this for me.
然后你看
And then,
接下来这些过程
every process is done by the AI controlling the computer.
全部都是由它操纵电脑完成的
我得强调一下
I have to emphasize,
我一个事都没做
that I didn't do anything.
那如果AI自己会装软件
If AI can install and operate software on its own,
会操作软件
那我为什么还要学软件
why would I need to learn?
那老实说
Honestly,
这确实没什么问题
there's nothing wrong with that.
这也是好事啊
It's a good thing.
时代在进步
Technology is moving forward.
你可能会说Tim
You might say, "Tim,
你们从业者就是想要有壁垒
people in your industry just want barriers to entry.
让你学的知识显得有价值
You want the knowledge you've learned to stay valuable."
也可以这么理解吧
That's a fair way to look at it.
谁不希望自己的作品有价值
Who doesn't want their work to have value?
哪怕是AI生成的你生的
Even if something was generated by AI,
你也会希望你生成的东西有价值
you'd still want what you created to have value.
但我们仔细想想
But think about it for a second.
如果我可以这么快速地
If I can acquire a software skill that quickly,
获得一个软件的技能
别人不行吗
why can't everyone else?
这就是很微妙的地方
And that's where things get tricky.
一旦通用型AI
Once general-purpose AI
开始接管软件
starts taking over software,
就是各行各业的软件
I mean software across every industry,
它会改变一件事
it changes one thing:
就是我们所有人
all of us
未来都会更质疑每一个作品
will become more skeptical of every piece of work.
因为一个底层的点被动了
Because something fundamental has changed:
可复制性
replicability.
以前一个作品做得好
Before, if someone made something great,
别人最多只能
the most others could do was slowly replicate it by hand.
慢慢手工地模仿
但现在可以这样操作
But now it works like this:
把这个火的作品
Take a viral piece of content,
不管是真人做的还是AI做的
whether it was made by a person or by AI,
交给AI
feed it to an AI,
然后我们和它说
and tell it,
帮我反推提示词
"Reverse-engineer the prompt for me."
然后一分钟之后
A minute later,
你的作品就被拆解成了文字和提示词
your work has been broken down into text and prompts.
然后这时候你说
Then you say,
帮我生成
"Generate something similar, but not exactly the same."
一个近似但又不同的作品
就出现了
Then it appears.
这也就是说一个人投入精力制作的原创内容
So, original content that someone spent real effort creating
可以快速被一个智能体所理解
can now be quickly understood,
提取
extracted,
并且使用
and reused by an AI agent.
然后再被上万个营销号
Then thousands of content farms
分身出无数个近似的作品
can spin off countless similar versions.
那原作真的能够
So can the original creator
抢到应有的关注吗
still get the attention they deserve?
不仅是视频
Not just about videos,
建筑
architecture,
文献
research papers,
任何东西
anything
都会遇到这样的状态
can end up in the same situation.
那如果一个
And if a viewer
已经看过AI复制品的观众
has already seen a bunch of AI copies,
在终于刷到这个原创内容的时候
then finally comes across the original,
是不是也会默认
won't they automatically
打上AI生成这个标签了
assume it was AI-generated too?
这会引申出更深的一个问题
That leads to an even deeper question.
请问这个AI反推出来的作品
If this AI-reconstructed work was indeed created by this person,
确实是由这个人操作的
这个作品的所属权
does ownership of the work really belong to them?
真的属于这个作者吗
这是原创吗
Is it original?
我个人
Personally,
感觉未来很多传统意义上的
I think a lot of what we traditionally consider
原创版权
copyright and originality
会被重新的定义
will end up being redefined.
有一种可能性
One possibility,
我觉得未来很有可能
and I think it's quite likely in the future,
不存在原创和版权的概念
the concepts of originality and copyright may not even exist,
只有肖像权和名誉权
what remains might just be rights of identity and reputation.
因为从传统著作权来鉴定和维权
Because traditional copyright law is too hard to enforce.
你会发现太难了
整个生产逻辑都已经变了
The entire production process has changed.
就以前创作的本质是
Before, the essence of creation
人和人经历产生的差异
came from differences in people's experiences.
现在AI正在快速抹平这种差别
Now AI is rapidly erasing those differences.
那该怎么办呢
So what do we do?
答案是
The answer is:
我不知道
I don't know.
所以我做这个视频来和你讨论
That's why I made this video.
国家其实响应很快的
Our country has responded pretty quickly.
已经推出了很多条例
Many regulations have been introduced.
这是绝对的好事
That's definitely a good thing.
比如标注 还有平台监管
We have things like AI labeling and platform oversight.
只能说AI现在有点太离谱了
All I can say is, AI has advanced so fast
所以内容信任这件事 比较棘手
that trust in online content has become a really difficult problem.
我很好奇你的想法
I'm curious about your ideas.
这个互联网内容信任危机怎么办
How do we deal with this crisis of trust online?
任何作品都可以被AI快速拆解重组
An era where AI can quickly break down and recreate any work,
让人分不出真假
leaving people unable to tell what's real,
只能留下评论“这是AI吗”的时代
and all they can ask is, "Is this AI?" seems to have arrived.
好像已经来了